Rienow, Robert; Papers ua902.009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Robert Rienow Papers
1875-1984
1955-1979
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Rienow, Robert, 1907-1989
ua902.009
15.72 cubic ft. 32 Cassettes
Correspondence with publishers and environmental groups including the Constitutional Council for Forest Preserves, 1970–71; Defenders of Wildlife, 1970–76; Albany Environmental Council, 1965–76; draft manuscripts and typescripts, 1956–79, of texts, scholarly and popular articles and books relating to local, state, national, and international government and to environmental issues such as the anti-nuclear movement, forest preservation, wildlife preservation, the Adirondack Mountains, lecture notes taken as a student and given to his classes, 1930–70, scripts for his television series "Man Against His Environment", 1970–71, drafts of speeches on environmental concerns, tape cassettes on environmental issues created as staff lecturer for the Center for Cassette Studies, clippings files on government and environmental issues, photographs of Rienow and his wife. Robert Rienow was educated at Carthage College (B.A., 1930), and Columbia University (M.A., 1934; Ph.D., 1937), served as Instructor, 1936–41, Assistant Professor, 1941–47, and Professor, 1947–80, of Social Science at the State University of New York at Albany, now the University at Albany. Through out his career Rienow maintained an active interest in environmental issues and a belief in the need to popularize issues of public concern. (See also papers of his wife Leona Train Rienow).
Biographical Sketch
Robert Rienow was born in Grafton, Wisconsin on December 4, 1907, and later in life married Leona Train, a writer of children's books and articles, and his occasional co-author. After a year at West Point, Rienow continued his education at Carthage College in Kenosha, Wisconsin, receiving a Bachelor of Arts degree in history in 1930. His first job was as a school principal at a small school in Wisconsin. Rienow went on to earn advanced degrees from Columbia University in the field of international law and government (M.A., 1933; Ph.D., 1937). While obtaining his master's degree, he taught for one year at Union College in Schenectady, New York. Rienow was also the recipient of Columbia University's Gilder Fellowship in Public Law. In 1935, Rienow attended Ohio State University as part of a research fellowship. ["Rienow to Discuss National Doctrine, Re-sing Scheduled", Unidentified News Clipping, 5 December 1947]. His Ph.D. dissertation was titled "The Test of the Nationality of a Merchant Vessel". While Rienow was completing his Ph.D. at Columbia he served as an Instructor of Political Science in the Social Sciences Department at the New York State College for Teachers, which later became the State University of New York at Albany and is presently known as the University at Albany, SUNY. Rienow continued in this position until 1941, when he was promoted to the position of Assistant Professor. Rienow was promoted to Professor in 1947 and held this position until 1980.
In July of 1943, Rienow took a leave of absence from his teaching position to serve in the United States Army during World War II. Rienow held a Selective Service position as a Classification Specialist, both in the United States and in the Pacific Theater, until 1945, when he was honorably discharged. He ended his career with the United States Army in 1946 at the rank of First Lieutenant in the Adjutant General's Office. Upon his return, Rienow served in the New York State National Guard in the Selective Service branch, rising to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. In 1962, Rienow, along with his unit, received an award on behalf of the National Guard for the superior ratings received by the unit at regular army inspections.
Rienow was a prolific writer who published books and articles on both political science and environmental issues. The most prominent of these was Moment in the Sun (1967), which he co-authored with his wife. Other significant works were Calling All Citizens (1952), New York State and Local Government (1959), Introduction to Government (1964), Our New Life with the Atom (1959), Of Snuff, Sin, and the Senate (1965), and The Lonely Quest (1966). The final three were co-authored by Rienow and Leona Train Rienow. Rienow also wrote numerous articles, both alone and in collaboration with his wife. Most of these articles expressed concern about environmental issues, though some were humorous or satirical pieces. Rienow's articles were published in magazines such as Harper's Weekly, This Week, the American Legion Magazine, the Saturday Review, and Ladies Home Journal.
Rienow maintained a vigorous interest in environmental issues throughout his life. A noted speaker, he delivered many lectures and presentations on environmental issues. In the late 1960s he developed a series of broadcasts on the environment in cooperation with the State University of New York at Albany's School of Public Policy. The series, Man Against His Environment, consisted of 28 lectures on topics such as water pollution, wildlife protection, overpopulation and zero population growth, as well as many others.
Rienow was a member of numerous environmental organizations, including Defenders of Wildlife, the Constitutional Council for Forest Preserves, the Audubon Society, the Sierra Club, and the Albany Environmental Council. He was an officer of the New York Chapter of The Nature Conservancy. Rienow's professional affiliations included the New York State Political Science Association, of which he was elected president in 1955. ["SCT President Heads Political Science Unit", Unidentified News Clipping, April 1955.]
Robert Rienow died in 1989 as the result of a fire in his home.
Scope and Contents
The papers in this collection document Rienow's professional career and personal interests. The collection contains personal files such as records relating to his service in both the United States Army and the New York National Guard; tax information; papers written by Rienow while he was in school; and family papers such as deeds. There are also a significant number of correspondence files. Much of the correspondence is with publishers and editors of various magazines and publishing houses. There is also correspondence with fellow members of environmental organizations and other personal correspondence, such as with Erastus Corning II, Mayor of the City of Albany, and fan mail received by Rienow and his wife.
The collection also contains papers related to Rienow's career at the State University of New York at Albany. These include extensive lecture notes, syllabi, copies of exams and some professional correspondence. Transcripts and some syllabi for the Man Against His Environment lecture series and a televised political science course called Living Patterns of Government can also be found within the collection. Files related to Rienow's writing career include manuscripts, drafts, and notes on his books and articles. In some cases the printed version of the article is available in the collection through copies of the publication, such as the American Legion Magazine.
There are also a series of audio tapes from the Center of Cassette Studies on a variety of environmental issues. Many of these tapes contain lectures from the Man Against His Environment series.
Also significant in the collection are subject files with mailings, notes, publications, photos, and articles on environmental issues, many of which were subjects of articles by Rienow. The subject files include information on organizations such as Defenders of Wildlife, the Nature Conservancy, and Zero Population Growth, as well as topics such as air and water pollution, wildlife protection, overpopulation and zero population growth, forest preservation and the preservation of the Adirondack Mountain region, and the anti-nuclear movement.
Strengths of the collection include the scripts from television and radio broadcasts; information regarding trends in environmental activism and Rienow's interests in the environmental movement; and the drafts and manuscripts of articles and speeches, many with annotations which illuminate Rienow's writing process.
Weaknesses of the collection include the lack of material on Rienow's personal life outside of his environmental interests as well as information on and materials from Rienow's life prior to 1960. There are also a significant number of news clippings and notes written on scraps of paper, and their significance is often unclear. Much of Rienow's voluminous correspondence related to his interest in environmental issues was lost in a fire at his home in 1989.
Researchers should see also the collection of Leona Train Rienow (MSS-025) in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. Though her collection includes manuscripts of her own publications (children's short stories and novels), it also contains manuscripts of some of her publications on the environment, many of which were written with her husband. This collection also contains correspondence from 1938 to 1963. Related collections can be found in the subject guides for Conservation and the Environment and University at Albany Faculty, Students, and Alumnae.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Biographical Files, 1875-1984
Series 2: Education Career, 1937-1980
Series 3: Writings, 1937-1980
Series 4: Broadcasts, 1958-1969
Series 5: Speeches and Lectures, 1938-1976
Series 6: Correspondence, 1939-1984
Series 7: Subject Files, 1937-1980
Series 8: Printed Materials, 1932-1959
Series 9: Audio Tapes, 1970-1973
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in June 1988.
Access
Access to student papers and class lists at the end of series 2 is restricted. Other series are unrestricted. Consult a staff member for details.
Political Science; Military and Armed Conflict; Conservation and the Environment; Political Science; Environmental education; Environmental management; Environmental protection; Conservation of natural resources--Citizen participation; Environmental health--Political aspects; Environmental policy--Social aspects; Environmental justice; Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Manuscripts; Drafts (documents); Clippings; Syllabi; Lecture notes; Examinations; Publications; Essays; Articles; Speeches; Lectures; Military records; Souvenirs; Scripts; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Rienow, Robert, 1907-1989; Rienow, Leona Train; State University of New York at Albany; Defenders of Wildlife; Nature Conservancy (U.S.); Zero Population Growth, Inc.
- Biographical Files, 1875-1984; 1; 1.6 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains papers pertaining to Robert Rienow and his family. Included are Rienow's military records from his World War II service in the United States Army and from the New York National Guard. These include discharge papers, appointment papers, immunization records, correspondence and memos. Also found in this series are legal documents and financial records from the estate of Rienow's uncle in Wisconsin, Fred Rienow. Rienow's education is documented through class notes and papers from West Point and from Columbia University, where he completed his Ph.D. There are several folders of brochures, news clippings, and souvenirs from Rienow's travels, including trips to Europe and the Midwest.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Honorary Degrees, 1963; 1971 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 1)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 2)
  - Military Service, National Guard, Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 3)
  - Military Service, Active Duty Correspondence and Supplementary Material, Overseas, 1944-1946 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 4)
  - Military Service, Discharge, 1946-1960 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 5)
  - Military Service, Financial Matters, Active Duty, 1943-1945 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 6)
  - Military Service, National Guard Selective Service, 1945-1968 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 7)
  - Military Service, Overseas Orders, 1936-1946 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, Robert and Leona Train Rienow, 1953-1977 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, Robert and Leona Train Rienow, 1953-1977 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, Robert and Leona Train Rienow, 1953-1977 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, Robert and Leona Train Rienow, 1953-1977 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 12)
  - Rienow Estate, Family Legal Documents, 1875-1975 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 13)
  - Rienow Estate, Family Legal Documents, 1875-1975 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 14)
  - Rienow Estate, Family Legal Documents, 1875-1975 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 15)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, 1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 16)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, 1932 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 17)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, 1932 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 18)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, ca. 1930s (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 19)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, ca. 1930s (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 20)
  - School Papers, Class Notes, International Law, ca. 1930s (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 21)
  - School Papers, Essays Written at West Point, 1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 22)
  - School Papers, M.A. Thesis, "The Presidential Power of Concluding Executive Agreements", 1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 23)
  - School Papers, M.A. Thesis, "The Presidential Power of Concluding Executive Agreements", 1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 24)
  - School Papers, Preliminary Examination in Political Theory, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 1)
  - School Papers, "Report in Research in International Law", 1934 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 2)
  - School Papers, "Seminar Report Covering Employment by France of Native African Troops in Her Defense", 1934 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 3)
  - School Papers, "What Would Hamilton's Philosophy Be Today?", 1933 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Albany and Related Materials, 1957-1982 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 5)
    Includes News Clippings, Correspondence, Bulletins.
  - Travel, 1950s-1970s (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 6)
    [Contains Clippings].
  - Travel, 1950s-1970s (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 7)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 8)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 9)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 10)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 11)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 12)
  - Travel, Europe, 1940-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 13)
  - Travel, Great Britain, Castles, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 14)
  - Travel, Midwest, 1950-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 15)
    [Contains clippings].
  - Travel, Midwest, 1950-1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Files), Folder 16)
    [Contains maps].
- Education Career, 1937-1980; 2; 2 cubic ft.
  This series contains files on courses taught by Rienow in the School of Public Policy and Affairs and the Department of Political Science at the State University of New York at Albany. The materials in this series include syllabi, lecture notes, examinations, and student papers. Related correspondence and clippings are also included. Files are arranged by course number, when known. There are several folders of final examinations not sorted by course number, as well as two folders of lecture notes and miscellaneous materials with no course number identified.
  Student papers and class lists are located at the end of the series. Included with student papers are two folders of essays on animal experimentation written for a national contest in 1979. Rienow was a judge for this competition. Access to student papers and course lists is restricted.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and course number.
  - Class Notes and Miscellaneous, ca. 1955-1967 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 1)
  - Class Notes and Miscellaneous, ca. 1955-1967 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 2)
  - Economics 1, Lectures and Notes, 1937-1938 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 3)
    [Includes clippings].
  - Economics 4, Undated (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 4)
    [includes clippings].
  - Education 405, Community Analysis, Notes, 1961; Undated (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 5)
  - Education 405, Community Analysis of Amsterdam, New York, A Committee Report, 1963 June (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 6)
  - Education 405, Community Analysis of Amsterdam, New York, A Committee Report, 1963 June (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 7)
  - Exams, 1939-1976 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 8)
  - Exams, 1939-1976 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 9)
  - Exams, 1939-1976 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 10)
  - Exams, 1939-1976 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 11)
  - Government 1, Lectures, and Notes, 1936-1937 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 12)
  - Government 3, Lecture Notes, 1937 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 13)
  - Governments of the World, Lecture Notes, Undated (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 14)
  - History 2B, Lecture Notes, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 15)
  - History 4 Lectures, 2nd semester, 1937-1938 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 16)
  - History 4 Ext., 1937-1939 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 17)
  - Labor Economics Extension Course, 1948 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, Educational Career, 1938-1941; Undated (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 19)
  - PAF 150, Bureaucracy, etc., 1972-1976 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 20)
  - PAF 150, Course materials, clippings, 1976-1979 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 21)
  - PAF 150, Lectures on the Environment, 1971-1980 (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 22)
    (includes notes, clippings, and bulletins).
  - PAF 150, Lectures on the Environment, Undated (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 23)
  - PAF 150, Notes and Lectures on Man vs. Environment, 1977 Fall (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 24)
    (also includes clippings, bulletins, and manuscripts).
  - PAF 150, Notes and Lectures on Man vs. Environment, 1977 Fall (Box 1 (2-Education Career), Folder 25)
  - PAF 150, Notes and Lectures, Miscellaneous, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 1)
    (includes clippings).
  - PAF 511, Land Use Policy, Notes on Land Use, 1977-1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 2)
  - POS 150, Lecture Notes, ca. 1966 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 3)
  - POS 380, International Law, Final Exam, 1974; 1976; 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 4)
  - P.S. 12, Lecture Notes, ca. 1965-1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 5)
  - P.S. 100A, Notes on Committees of Correspondence, 1940 January (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 6)
    [includes clover].
  - P.S. 131, Lecture Notes and Exams, 1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 7)
  - P.S. 214, Lecture Notes, ca. 1960-1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 8)
  - P.S. 216J, Lecture Notes, ca. 1959-1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 9)
  - P.S. 261 & 380, International Law, Notes on International Law, 1977 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 10)
    (also includes clippings and environmental notices).
  - P.S. 415, Lecture Notes, ca. 1965-1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 11)
  - Animal Experimentation, Student Essays for Contest, A-M, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 12)
  - Animal Experimentation, Student Essays for Contest, N-Z, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 13)
  - Independent Study Readings Course, Student Papers, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 14)
  - PAF 150, Class Lists, 1979-1980; Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 15)
  - PAF 150, Student Paper, "SERQA: An Insider's View", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 16)
  - PAF 150, Student Paper, "Term Project: The Bottle Bill", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 17)
  - PAF 510, Student Paper, "Intermediate Technology Toward a More Balanced Growth", 1976 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 18)
  - PAF 510, Student Paper, "Land Use Controls to Direct Growth", 1976 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 19)
  - PAF 510Q, Student Paper, "Wilderness in America", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 20)
  - PAF 511, Class Lists, Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 21)
  - PAF 650, Student Paper, "An Analysis of the Impact of Real Property Appraisal...", 1978 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 22)
  - PAF 650, Student Paper, "An Analysis of the Lands of the Town of Schodack", 1978 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 23)
  - POS 216, Student Bibliographies and Book Reviews, 1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 24)
  - POS 403, Student Bibliographies and Book Reviews, 1962 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 25)
  - POS 498, Student Paper. "Environmental Policy and the State Legislature", 1973 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 26)
  - POS 531, Student Paper, "The Battle Over the Repeal of the Metcalf-Hatch Act", 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 27)
  - POS 580, Student Assignments, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 28)
  - P.S. 12, Class List and Seating Chart, Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 29)
  - P.S. 131, Summaries of Class Discussions, 1966 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 30)
  - P.S. 214, Student Paper, "Comparison of the 4th and 5th French Republics...", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 31)
  - P.S. 216J, Student Bibliographies and Assignments, 1967 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 32)
  - P.S. 261, Student Paper, "The Falkland Islands Dispute", 1964 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 33)
  - P.S. 380, Class Lists, 1977 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 34)
  - P.S. 415, Student Paper, "An Analysis of Certain Bills Introduced in the 1965 Session of the New York State Legislature", ca. 1966 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 35)
  - P.S. 415, Student Paper, "An Analysis of Senate Bill 1833 and Assembly Bill 3353", 1965 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 36)
  - P.S. 415, Student Paper, "Grabbing on to an Idea: An Analysis of Legislation in Regard to Property Ownership as a Qualification for Voting", 1965 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 37)
  - P.S. 415, Student Paper, "Status Report on Property Ownership and Voting", 1965 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 38)
  - P.S. 415, Student Paper Outline, "County Government", 1965 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 39)
  - Seminar Paper, "Disarmament: A Study in Paradox", 1956 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 40)
  - Sketch of Robert Rienow and Poem, 1975 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 41)
  - Student Assignment, "Lobbying: State vs. Federal", 1962 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 42)
  - Student Assignments, Reports on Readings, 1960; 1963 (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 43)
  - Student Paper, "Expropriators Between the U.S. and the Three Latin American S Countries, Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 44)
  - Student Paper, "The Gross National Cost of GPN: Effects on Environmental and Psychological Sanity", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 45)
  - Student Paper, "Role and Influence of Interest Groups on Educational Policy", Undated (Box 2 (2-Education Career), Folder 46)
- Writings, 1937-1980; 3; 2.5 cubic ft.